<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="file:/C:/Users/brubi/AppData/Roaming/com.oxygenxml/autorecover/Schema%20Please.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<doc xmlns="https://ben-rub1n.github.io/ns/1.0">
    <header>
        <profileDesc>This document was encoded for Julia Flander's F2021 "Intro. to D.H." class at
            Northeastern University. More particularly, it was encoded for Assignment #4 which asks
            students, surprise surprise, to design a Relax NG schema and encoded documents using it
            while thinking through the impact of the choices made.</profileDesc>
        <fileDesc>
            <metaTitle>A TRUE COPIE OF THE PETITION OF THE GENTLEWOMEN, and Tradesmens-wives, in and
                about the City of LONDON.</metaTitle>
            <pubDate>1641-02-04</pubDate>
            <author>The Gentlewomen and Tradesmens-wives of 17th c. London</author>
            <genre>Formal Petition</genre>
            <publisher>R.O. and G.D.</publisher>
            <sponsor>John Bull</sponsor>
            <location>London</location>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>For an in-depth description of the encoding practices adhered to in this
            document, see my pseudoschema.</encodingDesc>
    </header>
    <body>
        <titlePage>
            <title>A TRUE COPIE OF THE PETITION OF THE GENTLEWOMEN, and Tradesmens-wives, in and
                about the City of LONDON <subtitle>Delivered, To the Honourable, the KNIGHTS,
                    Citizens, and Burgesses, of the house of Commons in Parliament, the 4th of
                    February, 1641.</subtitle><subtitle>Together, With their several Reasons why
                    their sex ought thus to Petition, aswell as the Men; and the manner how both the
                    Petition and Reasons was delivered.</subtitle><subtitle>Likewise the Answer
                    which the Honourable Assembly sent to them by Mr Pym, as they stood at the House
                    doore.</subtitle><subtitle>LONDON, Printed by R.O. G.D. for John Bull,
                    1641.</subtitle></title>
        </titlePage>
        <p>
            <heading>TO THE HONOURABLE KNIGHTS, CITIZENS, and BURGESSES, of the House of COMMONS
                assembled in PARLIAMENT. <subheading>The most humble PETITION of the GENTLEWOMEN,
                    TRADESMENS WIVES, and many others of the Female Sex, all Inhabitants of the
                    Citie of LONDON, and the Suburbs thereof.</subheading></heading>
        </p>
        <p>With lowest submission shewing,</p>
        <p>THAT we also with all thankfull humility acknowledging the unwearied paines, care and
            great charge, besides hazard of health and life, which you the noble worthies of this
            honourable and renowned Assembly have undergone, for the safety both of Church and
            Commonwealth, for a long time already past; for which not only we your humble
            Petitioners, and all well affected in this Kingdome, but also all other good Christians
            /(2)/ are bound now and at all times to acknowledge; yet notwithstanding that many
            worthy deeds have been done by you, great danger and feare do still attend us, and will,
            as long as Popish Lords and superstitious Bishops are suffered to have their voice in
            the House of Peers, and that accursed and abhominable Idole of the Masse suffered in the
            Kingdome, and that Arch-ene- Tower, yet not receiving his deserved punishment.</p>
        <p>All these under correction, gives us great cause to suspect, that GOD is angry with us,
            and to be the chiefe causes why your pious indeavours for a further Reformation
            proceedeth not with that successe as you desire, and is most earnestly prayed for of all
            that with well to true Religion, and the flourishing estate both of King and Kingdome;
            the insolencies of the Papists and their abettors, raiseth a just feare and suspition of
            sowing sedition, and breaking out into bloody persecution in this Kingdome, as they have
            done in IRELAND, the thoughts of which sad and barbarous events, maketh our tender
            hearts to melt within us, forcing us humbly to Petition to this honourable Assembly, to
            make safe provision for your selves and us, before it be too late.</p>
        <p>And whereas we, whose hearts have joined cheerefully with all those Petitions which have
            been exhibited unto you in the behalf of the purity of Religion, and the liberty of our
            Hubands persons and estates, recounting our selves to have an interest in the common
            privileges with them, doe with the same confidence assure our selves to finde the same
            gracious acceptance with you, for casing of those grievances, which in regard of our
            fraile condition, do more neerley concerne us, /(3)/ and do deeply terrifie our soules:
            our Domesticall dangers with which this Kingdome is so much distracted, especially
            growing on us from those treacherous and wicked attempts already are such, as we finde
            our selves to have as deepe a share as any other.</p>
        <p>We cannot but tremble at the very thoughts of the horrid and hideous facts which modestly
            forbids us now to name, occasioned by the bloody Warres in Germany, his Majesties late
            Northern Army, how often did it affright our hearts, wilst their violence began to break
            out so furiously upon the persons of those, whose Husbands or Parents were not able to
            rescure: wee with wee had no cause to speake of those insolencies, and savage usage and
            unheard of rapes, exercised upon our Sex in Ireland, and have we not just cause to feare
            they wil prove the forerunners of our ruine, except Almighty GOD by the wisdom and care
            of this Parliament be pleased to succor us, our Husbands and Children, which are as
            deere and tender unto us, as the lives and blood of our hearts, to see them murthered
            and mangled and cut in pieces before our eyes, to see our Children dashed against the
            stones, and the Mothers milke mingled with in Infants blood, running down the streets;
            to see our Houses on flaming fire over our heads: oh how dreadfull would this be / we
            thought it misery enough (though nothing to that we have just cause to feare) but few
            years since for some of our Sex, by unjust divisions from their bosome comforts, to be
            redred in a manner Widdows, and the children Fatherlesse, Husbands were imprisoned from
            the Society of their wives, even against the Lawes of GOD and Nature, and little Infants
            suffered in their Fathers’ banishments: /(4)/ thousands of our deerest friends have bin
            compelled to flyfrom Episcopall perfecutions into desert places amongst wilde Beasts,
            there finding more favour then in their native soyle, and in the midst of all their
            sorrowes, such hath the pitty of the Prelats been, that our cries could never enter into
            their eares or hearts, nor yet through multitudes of obstructions could never have
            accesss or come nigh to those Royall mercies of our most gracious Soveraigne, which we
            confidently hope, would have relieved us: but after all these pressures ended, we humbly
            signifie, that our present feares are, that unlesse the blood-thirsty faction of the
            Papists and Prelates be hindered in their designes, our selves here in England aswell as
            they in Ireland, shall be exposed to that misery which is more intolerable then that
            which is already past, as namely to the rage not of men alone, but of Divells incarnate,
            (as we may so say) besides the thraldome of our soules and consciences in matters
            concerning GOD, which of all things are most deare unto us.</p>
        <p>Now the remembrance of all these fearefull accidents aforementioned, do strongly move us
            from the example of the woman of Tekoa to fall submissively at the feete of his
            Majestie, our dread Soveraigne, and cry Helpe o King, helpe o yee noble Worthies now
            sitting in Parliament: And we humbly beseech you, that you will be a meanes to his
            Majestie and the House of Peeres, that they will be pleased to take our heartbreaking
            grievances into timely consideration, and to adde strength and incouragement to your noble
            indeavours and further that you would move his Majesty with our humble requests, that he
            would be graciously pleased /(5)/ according to the example of the good King Asa, to
            purge both the Court and Kingdome of that great Idolatrous Service of the Masse, which
            is tolerated in the Queenes Court, this finne (as we conceive) is able to draw downe a
            greater curse upon the whole Kingdome, then all your noble and pious indeavours can
            prevent, which was the cause that the good and pious King Asa would not suffer Idolatry
            in his own Mother, whose example if it shall please his Majesties gracious goodnesse to
            follow, in putting downe Popery and Idolatry both in great and small, in Court and in
            the Kingdome throughout, to subdue the Papists and their abetters, and by taking away
            power of the Prelats, whose government by long and wefull experience we have found to be
            against the liberty of our conscience and the freedome of the Gospell, and the sincere
            profession and practice thereof, then shall our feares be removed, and we may expect
            that GOD will power downe his blessings in abundance both upon his Majesty, and upon
            this Honourable Assembly, and upon the whole Land.</p>
        <p>For which your new Petitioners shall pray affectionately.</p>
        <p><heading>The Reason follow.</heading></p>
        <p>It may be thought strange, and unbeseeming our sex to shew our selves by way of Petition
            to the Honourable Assembly: but the matter being rightly considered, of the right and
            interest we have in the common and publique cause of the Church, it will, as we conceive
            (under correction) be found a duty commanded and required.</p>
        <p>First, because Christ hath purchased us at as deare a rate as he hath done Men, and
            therefore requireth the like obedience for the same mercy as of men.</p>
        <p>Secondly, because in the free enjoying of Christ in his own Laws, and a flourishing
            estate of the Church and Common-wealth, consisteth the happinesse of Women as well as
            Men.</p>
        <p>Thirdly, because Women are sharers in the common Calamities that accompany both Church
            and Common-wealth, when oppression is exercised over the Church or Kingdome wherein they
            live; and an unlimited power have been given to Prelats to exercise authority over the
            Consciences of Women, aswell as Men, witnesse Newgate, Smithfield, and other places of
            persecution, wherein Women aswell as Men have felt the smart of their fury.</p>
        <p>Neither are we left without example in Scripture, for when the state of the Church, in
            the time of King Ahasuerus was by the bloody enemies thereof sought to be utterly
            destroyed, we find that Ester the Queen and her Mayds fasted and prayed, and that Ester
            petitioned to the King in the behalf of the Church: and though she enterprised this duty
            with the hazard of her own life, /(7)/ being contrary to the Law to appeare before the
            King before she were sent for, yet her love to the Church carried her thorow all
            difficulties, to the performance of that duty.</p>
        <p>On which grounds we are imboldened to present our humble Petition unto this Honourable
            Assembly, not weighing the reproaches which may and are by many cast upon us, who (not
            well weighing the premisses) scoffe and deride our good intent. We do it not out of any
            selfe conceit, or pride of heart, as seeking to equall our selves with Men, either in
            Authority or wisdom: But according to our places to discharge that duty we owe to God,
            and the cause of the Church, as farre as lyeth in us, following herein the example of
            the Men, which have gone in this duty before us.</p>
        <p>A relation of the manner how it was delivered, with their Answer, sent by Mr.Pym.</p>
        <p>This Petition with their Reasons, was delivered the 4th of Reb, 1641. By Mris Anne Stagg,
            a Gentlewoman and BrewersWife, and many others with her of like rank and quality, which
            when they had delivered it, after some time spent in reading of it, the Honourable
            Assembly sent them an Answer by Mr PYM, which was performed in this manner.</p>
        <p>Mr PYM came to the Commons doore, and called for the Women, and spake unto them in these
            words: Good Women, your Petition and the Reasons have bin read in the House; and is very
            thankfully accepted of, and is come in a seasonable time: You shall (God willing)
            receive from us all the satisfaction which we can possibly give to your just and lawfull
            desires. We intreat you to repaire to your Houses, and tunre your petition which you
            have deliver here, in Prayers at home for us; for we have bin, are, and shall be (to our
            utmost power) ready to relieve you, your husbands, and Children, and to perform the
            trust committed unto us, towards, God, our King and Country, as becometh fauthfull
            Christians and Loyall Subjects.</p>
        <p>FINIS</p>
    </body>
</doc>
